GHULAM MUJTABA

Postdoctoral Researcher, West Virginia University, Morgantown, USA

+1-304-376-4935 | gmujtabakorai@gmail.com | www.gmujtaba.com

SUMMARY

6+ years of research and 3+ teaching experiences. Skilled deep learning and computer vision researcher and developed SOTA deep learning techniques to solve complex problems. Published 10+ papers in top academic journals and conferences, and have one USA patent pending.

Research Interests Computer Vision, Deep Learning for Visual Analysis, and Multimedia Retrieval

Technical Skills Languages: Python, Java, C#

Libraries: PyTorch, TensorFlow, Keras, OpenCV, Pillow, NumPy

Others: Git, LaTeX, Linux, Unity3D

EDUCATION

Doctor of Philosophy in Engineering

Mar 2018 — Aug 2021

Gachon University, Seongnam, South Korea

Dissertation: Lightweight Client-driven Personalized Multimedia Framework for Next Generation Streaming Platforms

Advisor: Prof. Jaehyuk Choi, Co. Advisor: Prof. Eun-Seok Ryu

Master of Science in Computer Science

Jul 2014 — Jun 2016

Indus University, Karachi, Pakistan

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science

Sep 2009 — Jul 2013

COMSATS Institute of Information Technology, Lahore, Pakistan

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Postdoctoral Researcher West Virginia University

Apr 2023 - Present

Morgantown, WV, USA

- Improved Diagnostic Accuracy: Conduct cutting-edge research and develop SOTA deep learning models for medical image/video data analysis, like specializing in multi-label classification of ChexNet X-ray images.
- ChatGPT, Generative AI, and LLMs: Explored the latest technology advancements, applications, and implications while creating a research roadmap for further exploration.
- Enhanced Research Output: Actively contributed to a 40% increase in research productivity by co-authoring one research paper and working on two projects.

Research Engineer

Mar 2022 – Mar 2023

C-JeS Gulliver Studio

Seoul, South Korea

- Achieved 20% higher realism in digital-human characters: Applied advanced deep learning technique resulting in elevating digital-human realism in Metaverse applications.
- Reduced production time by 30%: Innovated and deployed efficient 2D to 3D conversion methods, slashing project timelines and production costs while maintaining high-quality digital-human designs, directly contributing to project success and profitability.
- Elevated studio's research profile: Authored 2 research papers (one journal and one conference), elevating the studio's reputation as a thought leader in digital-human technology, attracting top talent, and fostering innovation across the industry.

Senior Researcher

Oct 2021 – Feb 2022

DeltaX.ai

Seoul, South Korea

- XVision Technology Advancement: Developed deep learning techniques utilizing CNNs, RNNs, LSTMs, and SVMs to recognize sequential patterns for human activity, with a particular emphasis on violence detection in videos and images.
- Award-Winning Collaboration: Collaborated on the Self-Driving Data Contest 2021, contributing to a project that earned the Korea Transportation Safety Authority Chairman Award.
- Market Growth Opportunities: Identified and prototyped innovative opportunities for company growth in emerging markets.

Visiting Researcher

Sep 2019 – Sep 2021

Multimedia Computing Systems Laboratory, Sungkyunkwan University

Seoul, South Korea

• On device computation: Pioneered thumbnail-based video analysis for streaming platforms, achieved 3.57% boost in computational efficiency. Successfully deployed deep learning models on Nvidia Jetson TX2 modules, accelerating the development of advanced video content analysis systems.

- Intellectual Property Protection: Developed meticulous disclosure documents for multinational collaborations, safeguarding critical intellectual property and enabling successful technology transfer.
- **Publication Impact:** Authored research manuscripts (4 journals, 11 conferences), significantly raising the lab's academic profile and contributing to its recognition as a prominent research entity.

Graduate Research Assistant

Mar 2018 - Jun 2021

Department of Computer Engineering, Gachon University

Seongnam, South Korea

- Healthcare Solutions for Seniors: Participated in developing AI-based healthcare solutions for seniors by designing and
 implementing a comprehensive life-logging system. Enabled detailed activity monitoring using advanced video analysis for
 improved senior well-being and safety.
- Multiview Video Summarization: Collaborated in the development of algorithms for multiview video surveillance summarization, leveraging target-appearance-based features, user-preferred emotional moments, facial expression recognition, and extensive exploration of pre-trained deep models.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Lecturer

Oct 2017 - Jan 2018

Department of Computer Science, Mohammad Ali Jinnah University

Karachi, Pakistan

- Taught undergraduate courses, including Mobile Application Development, Theory of Automata, and Computer Programming.
- Developed comprehensive course outlines aligned with the accreditation standards, ensuring clear objectives and outcomes to enhance the quality of education.
- Provided guidance and supervision to undergraduate students in their final year projects, mentoring them in project development and research methodologies.

Full-Time Cooperative Teacher

Aug 2016 - Sep 2017

Faculty of CS & IT, Benazir Bhutto Shaheed University Lyari

Karachi, Pakistan

- Instructed undergraduate courses, including Object-Oriented Programming, Data Structure & Algorithm, and Information Security.
- Developed course outlines in accordance with the requirements set by relevant accreditation bodies, aligning objectives and outcomes to meet educational standards.
- Provided guidance and oversight to undergraduate students in their final year projects, assisting them in project management and implementation.

Junior Lecturer

Jan 2015 – Jul 2016

Faculty of Engineering Science & Technology, Indus University

Karachi, Pakistan

- Instructed undergraduate courses, including Mobile Game Development, Object-Oriented Programming, and Programming Fundamentals.
- Developed comprehensive course outlines aligned with the requirements of accreditation bodies, ensuring clear objectives and measurable outcomes.
- Provided supervision and guidance to undergraduate students in their final year projects, supporting them throughout the project lifecycle.

DEVELOPMENT EXPERIENCE

Developer

Mar 2014 - Oct 2014

Karachi, Pakistan

The Game Storm Studio (PVT) LTD

- Conceptualized and designed the initial gameplay and mechanics of the game, utilizing Unity3D, Unity2D, and Cocos2dx.
- Resolved complex technical challenges that arose during game production, ensuring smooth development and functionality.
- Collaborated closely with team members to effectively fulfill project requirements and deliver high-quality results.

Jr. Software Engineer

Jul 2013 - Jan 2014

Symbiosis Technologies (PVT) LTD

Karachi, Pakistan

- Supported the initial design phase of the application and contributed to the integration of various components.
- Developed and rigorously tested program modules in accordance with the specified application requirements.

PUBLICATIONS

USA Patent

• **Ghulam Mujtaba**, Eun-Seok Ryu, and Reda Harb "Personalized Semantic Fast-Forward Videos for Next Generation Streaming Platforms", [AF] Aug. 30, 2022, [AN] 17/899,292.

Under Review

1. **Ghulam Mujtaba**[†], Sunder Ali Khowaja[†], Aslam Jarwar, Jaehyuk Choi, and Eun-Seok Ryu "FRC-GIF: Frame Ranking-based Personalized Artistic Media Generation Method for Resource Constrained Devices", IEEE Transactions on Big Data

Preprint Articles

- 1. S. M. A. Sharif, **Ghulam Mujtaba**, and S. M. Nadim Uddin, "EdgeNet: A novel approach for Arabic numeral classification", arXiv preprint arXiv:1908.02254, **2019**
- 2. Salman Mohamadi, **Ghulam Mujtaba**, Thi Hoang Ngan Le, Gianfranco Doretto, and Donald A. Adjeroh, "ChatGPT in the Age of Large Language Models and Generative AI: A Concise Survey", arXiv preprint arXiv:2307.04251, **2023**
- 3. Sunder Ali Khowaja, **Ghulam Mujtaba**, Jiseok Yoon, and Ik Hyun Lee, "Face-PAST: Facial Pose Awareness and Style Transfer Networks", arXiv preprint arXiv:2307.09020, **2023**
- 4. Shabir Ahmad, Sabina Umirzakova, **Ghulam Mujtaba**, Muhammad Sadiq Amin, Taegkeun Whangbo, "Education 5.0: Requirements, Enabling Technologies, and Future Directions", arXiv preprint arXiv:2307.15846, **2023**

Peer-reviewed Journals

- 1. **Ghulam Mujtaba**, Adeel Malik, and Eun-Seok Ryu "LTC-SUM: Lightweight Client-driven Personalized Video Summarization Framework Using 2D CNN" IEEE Access, Vol. 10, **2022**, pp. 103041-103055, IF: 3.476
- 2. **Ghulam Mujtaba**, Sangsoon Lee, Jaehyoun Kim, and Eun-Seok Ryu, "Client-driven Animated GIF Generation Framework Using an Acoustic Feature", Multimedia Tools and Applications, **2021**, IF: 2.313
- 3. **Ghulam Mujtaba**, and Eun-Seok Ryu, "Client-Driven Personalized Trailer Framework Using Thumbnail Containers", IEEE Access, Vol. 8, **2020**, pp. 60417-60427, IF: 4.098
- 4. **Ghulam Mujtaba**, Muhammad Tahir, and Muhammad Hanif Soomro, "Energy-Efficient Data Encryption Techniques in Smartphones", Wireless Personal Communications 106.4,

Peer-reviewed Conferences

- 1. **Ghulam Mujtaba**, Jaehyuk Choi, and Eun-Seok Ryu, "Client-driven Lightweight Method to Generate Artistic Media for Feature-length Sports Videos", SIGMAP'22: 19th International Conference on Singal Processing and Multimedia Applications **2022**, Libson, Portugal
- 2. **Ghulam Mujtaba**, and Eun-Seok Ryu, "Human Character-oriented Animated GIF Generation Framework", IEEE MAJICC'21: Mohammad Ali Jinnah University Conference on Informatics and Computing **2021**, Karachi, Pakistan
- 3. Badaruddin, Abdul Aziz, Tuan Thanh Le, and **Ghulam Mujtaba**, "Movie Genre Classification from Movie Posters Using Deep Feedforward Network", The 16th Asia Pacific International Conference on Information Science and Technology (APIC-IST 2021), Jun 20-22, **2021**
- 4. **Ghulam Mujtaba**, Eun-Soo Park, Seunghwan Kim, and Eun-Seok Ryu, "Client-driven Music Genre Classification Framework", The Korean Institute of Broadcast and Media Engineers (KIBME) Summer Conference, Jul 13-15, **2020**
- 5. Eun-Soo Park, SeungHwan Kim, **Ghulam Mujtaba**, and Eun-Seok Ryu, "Analysis of Action Recognition Model Performance Differences According to Preprocessing Methods", Summer Workshop on Computer Communications (SWCC), Aug 27, **2020**
- 6. SeungHwan Kim, Eun-Soo Park, **Ghulam Mujtaba**, Eun-Seok Ryu, "Weight Compression Method with Video Codec", The Korean Institute of Broadcast and Media Engineers (KIBME) Fall Conference, Nov 27-28, **2020**
- 7. SeungHwan Kim, Eun-Soo Park, **Ghulam Mujtaba**, Eun-Seok Ryu, "Video Codec Based Deep Learning Weight Compression", Summer Workshop on Computer Communications (SWCC), Aug 27, **2020**
- 8. Eun-Soo Park, Seunghwan Kim, **Ghulam Mujtaba**, Eun-Seok Ryu, "Detection of Power Transmission Equipment in Image using Guided Grad-CAM", The Korean Institute of Broadcast and Media Engineers (KIBME) Summer Conference, Jul 13-15, **2020**
- 9. SeungHwan Kim, Eun-Soo Park, **Ghulam Mujtaba**, Eun-Seok Ryu, "Compression Method for CNN Models Using DCT", The Korean Institute of Broadcast and Media Engineers (KIBME) Summer Conference, Jul 13-15, **2020**
- 10. **Ghulam Mujtaba**, and Eun-Seok Ryu, "Personalized Movie Trailer Using Thumbnail Containers", Al4TV 2019: Proceedings of the 27th ACM International Conference on Multimedia, **2019**, [Demo Paper], Nice, France
- 11. Eun-Soo Park, Seunghwan Kim, Jaesung Ryu, Seondae Kim, **Ghulam Mujtaba**, Eun-Seok Ryu, "Action Recognition Reference Image Captioning", The Korean Institute of Broadcast and Media Engineers (KIBME) Summer Conference, pp. 21-24, Jun 19-21, **2019**
- 12. **Ghulam Mujtaba**, Seondae Kim, Eun-Soo Park, Seunghwan Kim, Jaesung Ryu, and Eun-Seok Ryu, "Client-driven Animated Keyframe Generation System Using Music Analysis", The Korean Institute of Broadcast and Media Engineers (KIBME) Summer Conference, pp. 176-178, Jun 19-21, **2019**
- 13. Seondae Kim, Il-Woong Ryu, Jaesung Ryu, **Ghulam Mujtaba**, Eun-Soo Park, Seunghwan Kim, and Eun-Seok Ryu, "Aesthetic Feature-based Activity Summarization for Senior Life Logging", The Korean Institute of Broadcast and Media Engineers (KIBME) Summer Conference, pp. 25-28, Jun 19-21, **2019**
- 14. **Ghulam Mujtaba**, Muhammad Tahir, Muhammad Hanif Soomro, "Energy-efficient data encryption techniques in Smartphones", Global Conference on Wireless and Optical Communications (GCWOC'17), **2017**, Malaga, Spain

SELECTED PROJECTS

1. Digital Human Solution for Metaverse

Mar 2022 - Mar 2023

Researched cutting-edge technologies to design realistic digital humans for the Metaverse at C-JeS Gulliver Studios. Developed an innovative image-based deep learning method and collaborated with the VFX team to seamlessly integrate digital humans into various virtual reality applications.

2. xVision, AI-Based Video Analysis Solution

Oct 2021 — Feb 2022

Designed and developed the xVision method using deep learning and computer vision techniques at DeltaX.ai. Designed using TensorFlow convolutional neural networks and LSTM networks to analyze feature-length videos, facilitating object and scene detection.

3. Dynamic Sports Highlights Generation

Mar 2019 — Sep 2022

Lightweight client-driven method proposed to generate artistic media for feature-length sports videos at SKKU, Seoul South Korea. Designed an effective 2D Convolutional Neural Network model for LTC analysis that can classify personalized events from six different sports categories. Reduced the computational complexity by 3.78 times than SOTA on a resource constrained device like NVIDIA Jetson TX2.

4. Personalized Media Communication

Jan 2018 — May 2019

Designed and prototyped a lightweight client-driven framework for a personalized media streaming framework at Gachon University, South Korea funded by InterDigital, CA, USA. The method was configured on the HTTP live streaming (HLS) steaming protocol on the server and client sides.

5. Development of Energy-efficient Techniques Using Data Encryption in Smartphones

Jul 2017 — Feb 2018

Researched and developed a native Android app during my master's program funded partially by HEC, Pakistan. Designed the app to implement diverse encryption algorithms for data encryption. Conducted power consumption measurements on smartphones to evaluate algorithm efficiency across varying file sizes.

AWARD AND ACHIEVEMENTS

Recipient, Doctoral Consortium at International Conference on Computer Vision (ICCV)	2021
Recipient, President's Award for Academic Excellence, Gachon University, South Korea	2021
Recipient, Outstanding Research Award, MCSL SKKU, South Korea	2020
Recipient, Travel Grant, Higher Education Commission (HEC) Pakistan	2017
 Runner up, Gaming Competition (CoD4) Technomoot '13, Abot., Pakistan 	2013
• Finalist, Offices of Research, Innovation & Commercialization (ORICS) of Hell Zone (Game), Lahore, Pakistan	2012
 Winner, Gaming Competition (Stronghold Crusader) Technomoot '12, Abot., Pakistan 	2012
 Runner up, Gaming Competition (Counter Strike) VISIO Spark' 12, Wah, Pakistan 	2012
Runner up, Quiz Competition COMSPEC '10, Lahore, Pakistan	2010
 Recipient, Scholarship for bachelor's degree by Ministry of IT, Pakistan 	2009 - 2013

ACADEMIC ACTIVITIES

IEEE Senior IEEE Member	2023 — Present
• Session Chair 19th International Conference on Signal Processing & Multimedia Applications, Lisbon, Portugal	2022
Reviewer IEEE Transactions on Network Science and Engineering	2021 — Present
Reviewer IEEE Journal of Biomedical and Health Informatics	2023 — Present
Reviewer IEEE Access	2019 — Present
<u>Reviewer Springer Wireless Personal Communications</u>	2017 — Present
Reviewer IEEE International Conference on Multimedia and Expo, Brisbane, Australia	2023
Reviewer IEEE International Conference on Communications ICC'23, Rome, Italy	2023
• Reviewer STI'22: 4th International Conference on Sustainable Technologies for Industry 4.0, Dhaka, Bangladesh	2022
Reviewer INMIC'20: 23rd IEEE International Multi Topic Conference, Bahawalpur, Pakistan	2020
• Reviewer GCWOC'18: 3rd Global Conference on Wireless and Optical Communications, Malaga, Spain	2018

REFERENCES

Prof. Eun-Seok Ryu Sungkyunkwan University (SKKU), Seoul, South Korea, +82-10-4839-2199, esryu@skku.edu

Prof. Muhammad Aslam Jarwar Sheffield Hallam University, Sheffield, United Kingdom, +44-7561-003029, a.jarwar@shu.ac.uk

Prof. Sander Ali Khuwaja Korea Polytechnic University, South Korea, +92-333-1381424, sandar.ali@usindh.edu.pk

Dr. Prince Waqas Khan West Virginia University, USA, +1-681-350-2941, princewaqas.khan@mail.wvu.edu

Abdul Hai Memon DICK'S Sporting Goods, USA, +1-331-703-5704, ahaimemon@gmail.com